<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Complex Networks at Cambridge</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Complex Networks at Cambridge</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cambridge Networks Relaunch</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-11-27eventcambridge-networks-relaunch/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-11-27eventcambridge-networks-relaunch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-this-event&#34;&gt;About this event&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the first academic event of the year, where we welcome back a revitalised cohort across Cambridge working on complex networks.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Further details will be announced soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Krakencoder: a multi-modal connectome fusion tool for brain-behavior mapping</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2026-01-08seminarthe-krakencoder-a-multi-modal-connectome-fusion-tool-for-brain-behavior-mapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2026-01-08seminarthe-krakencoder-a-multi-modal-connectome-fusion-tool-for-brain-behavior-mapping/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk, Dr. Kuceyeski will introduce the Krakencoder – her lab’s new tool for multi-modal integration of brain network measurements that allows mapping between connectome processing pipelines as well as between structural and functional connectomes. This AI tool allows state of the art preservation of inter-individual differences in brain networks through a shared latent space. In an extension from the original publication earlier this year, she will demonstrate the flexibility of the tool for jointly minimizing site differences (harmonization) as well as maximizing brain-behavior mapping accuracy for various metrics. She also demonstrate how the tool can be used to create interpretable feature importances when mapping to behavior or demographics. This tool represents the power of AI in better understanding the mapping between brain structure and function and behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex Structure and Dynamics in Brain Networks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-12-04seminarcomplex-structure-and-dynamics-in-brain-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-12-04seminarcomplex-structure-and-dynamics-in-brain-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How does the brain work as an integrated system? Understanding the organization of brain graphs (networks), their community structure and time-varying topology is key to tackling this challenge. Network Neuroscience is an emerging field dedicated to understanding the structure and function of neural systems across scales, from neurons to circuits and ultimately to the whole brain. In this presentation I will review a few current themes and future directions. These include connectomics, structure/function relationships as disclosed in neuroimaging data, the growing use of computational models to map information flow and communication dynamics, and a novel edge-centric approach to track dynamic functional connectivity. I will try to identify some key issues along three main dimensions: networks, dynamics, and information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Changing Connectomes: Changes during development as well as changes after brain stimulation interventions to improve cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-11-20seminarchanging-connectomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-11-20seminarchanging-connectomes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The complete set of connections in the brain is called our connectome. Over the last 20 years we have found out more about how this network is organised and how it develops. I will outline some characteristic network features and how they could originate during brain network development. In particular, I will highlight the impact of the spatial organisation and embedding of brain networks and the role of delays on brain dynamics and cognition. Moreover, I will outline how interventions based on connectome information and computational models might be able to improve cognitive function for brain and mental health conditions. For this, I will also discuss how network metrics change after stimulation as well as our ongoing work on developing closed-loop neuromodulation for brain and mental health (depression, schizophrenia, Tourette’s). Finally, I will give some information on the launch of our N3 Centre for Neurotechnology, Neuromodulation, and Neurotherapeutics at the University of Nottingham.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal Discovery and Network Inference for Biological and Biomedical Data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-11-06seminarcausal-discovery-and-network-inference-for-biological-and-biomedical-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-11-06seminarcausal-discovery-and-network-inference-for-biological-and-biomedical-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Discovering causal effects is at the core of scientific investigation but remains challenging when mostly observational data is available. In essence, causal discovery infers cause-effect relations from specific correlation patterns involving at least three variables, which goes beyond the popular notion that pairwise correlation does not imply causation. Yet, in practice, causal representations have been difficult to learn and interpret, in particular, for high dimensional data such as state-of-the-art biological and biomedical data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Divided Mind</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-10-23seminarthe-divided-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-10-23seminarthe-divided-mind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I will talk about this recently published book: why did I write it, what was I trying to say that it would have been difficult to communicate in a peer-reviewed paper, and who was I hoping might read it? I will summarise the content and key themes of the book along the following lines, but I hope to leave a good amount of time for discussion. Briefly, the book tries to tell two occasionally interwoven histories. First, the world history of what we now call schizophrenia, especially the controversy between Freudian (brainless) and Kraepelinian (mindless) tribes, the dark crisis of the Kraepelinian concept of dementia praecox before and during World War 2, and its long-lasting imprint on how we continue to think about schizophrenia to this day. Second, my personal story as I became a psychiatrist and tried to get to grips with scientific questions about the origins of schizophrenia and the prospects for better treatments or preventions in future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neurotransmitter receptor gradients enable flexible control of cortex-wide network dynamics during cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-06-12seminarneurotransmitter-receptor-gradients-enable-flexible-control-of-cortex-wide-network-dynamics-during-cognition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2025-06-12seminarneurotransmitter-receptor-gradients-enable-flexible-control-of-cortex-wide-network-dynamics-during-cognition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in neuroanatomy and physiology make it possible to probe whole-brain mechanisms of cognition and behavior. However, as yet, few models in computational neuroscience have tackled the mechanisms underlying highly distributed neural activity during cognitive tasks. In this talk I will describe our anatomy-led approach to developing multiscale connectome-based models of neural dynamics during cognitive tasks and our recent anatomical findings of gradients of neurotransmitter receptors in the cortex.  I will highlight our investigations into how inputs from neuromodulatory systems (e.g. dopamine, serotonin) may dynamically alter the connectome, shifting the cortical dynamical landscape, and how this can confer flexibility on distributed cognitive functions such as conscious perception and working memory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cambridge Networks Day 2019</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2019-08-29eventcambridge-networks-day-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2019-08-29eventcambridge-networks-day-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-this-event&#34;&gt;About this event&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cambridge Networks Day 2019 is the sixth of our annual meetings on the topic of complex networks. It&#xA;is an occasion for the research community to exchange ideas and expertise, intended to spark interdisciplinary collaborations. The day will include a diverse set of talks by invited speakers highlighting interesting new directions in the field of complex networks, as well as a poster session. We hope the day’s events will strengthen the interdisciplinary links between researchers and promote communication within the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Epidemics over Mobile Phone Networks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2015-10-03seminarepidemics-over-mobile-phone-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2015-10-03seminarepidemics-over-mobile-phone-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Human interactions sensed ubiquitously by mobile phones can improve a significant number of public health problems, particularly helping to track the spread of disease. In this talk, we evaluate multiple avenues for the integration of high-resolution face to face Bluetooth-sensed interaction networks into epidemic models. Our goal is to evaluate the capacity of the different avenues of integration to track the spread of seasonal influenza on a real-world community of 72 individuals over a period of 17 weeks. The dataset considered contains real-time tracking of individual flu symptoms over the whole observation period, providing a concrete individualized source for evaluation. We present two different studies on this dataset. The first considers the standard SIR model simulated over real network dynamics with the overall goal of predicting the real infections over time. We obtain an error of less than 2 infected people on average when predicting the total number of individuals affected by the flu and a precision of approximately 30% when predicting exactly which individual will become infected at a given time. Our results indicate that high-resolution mobile phone data can increase the predictive power of even the simplest of epidemic models. The second study proposes a dual model for contact tracing, where an infection is spreading in the physical interpersonal network&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Technology Pathway of Society from U.S. Patents</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2015-02-17seminarunderstanding-technology-pathway-of-society-from-u.s.-patents/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2015-02-17seminarunderstanding-technology-pathway-of-society-from-u.s.-patents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Technology’s advance is central to our understanding of economic growth and development. Furthermore, solutions for many of the planet’s most pressing challenges – economic recovery, poverty reduction, climate change, sustainability – require significant additions to society’s technological toolkit. Yet, our ability to quantitatively model and forecast technological change has been limited due to difficulties in defining units of analysis and in collecting comparative empirical data. Some inventions, namely patents, however, leave behind a documentary trail, enabling us to study the invention processes in a quantitative way. Here, we propose to develop a formal methodology to construct detailed technology &amp;ldquo;map&amp;rdquo; and its temporal evolution from large-scale U.S. Patent data spanning 220 years. We utilize the classification system consisting of codes as temporally consistent units of analysis (nodes). These technology codes are means to succinctly describe a patent’s technology capabilities. When codes appear together in a patent, therefore, we consider them inter-dependent to make a useable function and represent this inter-dependency by assigning a link to between them. These micro-scale invention activities add up to form networks in time where macro-scale structures emerge through temporal evolution of community structure. We observe and identify episodic change of structure over time corresponding to historic events and major breakthroughs, indicating the technology change is not gradual but serious of punctuated equilibriums.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Series meet Network Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2015-01-27seminartime-series-meet-network-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2015-01-27seminartime-series-meet-network-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last years, ideas and methods from network science have been applied to study the structure of time series and signals, thereby building a bridge between nonlinear dynamics, time series analysis and graph theory. In this talk I will focus on a particular approach, namely the family of visibility algorithms, and will give an overview of the main results that we have obtained recently. In particular, I will depict several case studies where concrete problems in nonlinear dynamics, stochastic processes and statistical physics can be easily mapped, via visibility algorithms, to the study of the topological properties of classes of visibility graphs. I will conclude with a summary of open problems and applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dominance Hierarchy Networks of Worker Ants</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2014-12-02seminardominance-hierarchy-networks-of-worker-ants/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/camnetsnet/events/2014-12-02seminardominance-hierarchy-networks-of-worker-ants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Group-living animals, from insects to mammals, often form dominance hierarchy, which is a directed network. The direction of the link represents aggression by one individual on the other subordinate individual. In small groups of animals, it has been long known that the hierarchy is often perfectly linear, allowing unique ranking of the individuals. However, perfect linearity is often violated in large groups. I present analysis of aggressive dominance hierarchy formed by worker ants as large directed networks and then discuss evolutionary implications of the results. I also present some results on generative models to account for the observed connectivity patterns, built on the assumption of heterogeneously distributed intrinsic strengths of individual nodes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
